Self-Determination for D.C. (SDDC) 003
People's Archive, MLK Library
Self-Determination for D.C. (SDDC) Collection
1970-1980
People's Archive, MLK Library
Self-Determination for D.C.
003
25 Boxes
12.5 Linear feet
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated to the Library in 1989 by Richard W. Clark, Chairman of the Self-Determination for D.C. National Coalition.
Arrangement
Series 1: Topical Files, 1975-1985 (1.5LF) Consists of topical files related to the issue of voting rights, home rule, and statehood for D.C. Series contains congressional testimony, legislation, correspondence to D.C. and federal legislators, brochures, flyers, and handwritten notes.
Series 2: Opposition Groups, 1976-1986 (0.5 LF) Contains materials about organizations and individuals the Coalition considered opponents of self-determination for D.C..
Series 3: Support Groups, 1976-1985 (2.5 LF) Consists of reports, clippings, correspondence, pamphlets, and printed materials from organizations the Coalition considered supporters of its goals.
Series 4: Chronological Files, 1970-1973 (0.25LF) Contains internal memoranda, drafts, letters, and Coalition Comments, the Coalition's newsletter.
Series 5: Lobbying Files, 1972-1973 (1.75LF) Contains materials documenting the Coalition's lobbying efforts for home rule in 1973. Included are reports, issued papers, congressional contact lists, lobbying packets, and background materials on the House District Committee, among others.
Series 6: Media Coverage, 1972-1973 (0.5LF) Contains media lists from various states
Series 7: Legislation, 1965-1973 (1.25LF) Contains briefing papers, legislative analyses, congressional legislation, letters, Congressional Record excerpts, congressional voting records, and other legislative materials related to home rule.
Series 8: Post-Home Rule Passage, 1974 (0.25LF) Contains reports, clippings and correspondence on 1974 campaign financing, the formation of advisory neighborhood commissions, and other topics.
Series 9: Related Organizations, 1960-1971 (0.25LF) Contains materials regarding the two organizations which preceded the Coalition; the Home Rule Committee and Ad-Hoc Committee for Home Rule.
Series 10: Research, 1966-1973 (0.25LF) Consists of research documents prepared by the Library of Congress regarding home rule and voting rights for D.C.. Also contains legislative bills, reprints, and copies of articles on the same issues.
Series 11: Publications, 1973 (0.25LF) Primarily consists of brochures, newsletters of SDDC and other related organizations.
Series 12: Memorabilia, ca. 1970 (1.75LF) contains brochures, buttons, bumper stickers, a patriot's hat, and banner of the Coalition. Also contains the publication Salute to Volunteers prepared by the Coalition.
Biographical / Historical
Self-Determination for D.C. coalition was formed as the result of the adoption of a resolution in January 1971 by the Americans for Democratic Action calling for the formation of a national coalition to promote home rule and congressional voting representation for the District of Columbia. Initially the Coalition was called the Democracy for D.C. Committee and consisted of 25 local and national groups along with several city residents. Richard W. Clark, a special assistant to the president of Common Cause, and Victor Reuther, a labor leader, agreed to serve as national co-chairman. In the fall of 1971 a metropolitan steering committee was formed of local organizations with Sterling Tucker and Marne Hornblower serving as co-chairmen. The coalition was instrumental in lobbying for and campaigning for home rule legislation and a constitutional amendment providing for congressional representation in Congress. The coalition disbanded in 1985.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of office files documenting the activities of the Self-Determination for D.C. Coalition in support of home rule and voting rights issues. In particular, the collection consists of testimony, legislation, lobbying packets, correspondence, and media lists regarding its lobbying efforts in support of Congressional legislation passed in 1973 granting D.C. home rule (D.C. Self-Government and Reorganization Act). The records also contain materials compiled by the coalition regarding supportive and opposition organizations, reports, clippings, press releases, newsletters, and other printed materials and ephemera.
Politics and government; Associations, institutions, etc; Statehood (American politics); Home rule -- Washington (D.C.); Suffrage; United States. Congress. House--District of Columbia voting rights
- Series 1: Topical Files, 1975-1985
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of topical files related to the issue of voting rights, home rule, and statehood in the District of Columbia. Contains congressional testimony, legislation, correspondence to D.C. and federal legislators, brochures, flyers, and handwritten notes.
  - Government Reorganization Act, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Home rule - background, 1962-1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Home rule - background, 1962-1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Home rule - background, 1962-1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Home rule - background, 1962-1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Home rule - background, 1962-1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Home rule - background, 1962-1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Home rule - background, 1962-1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Home rule - background, 1962-1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Home Rule, October 1982 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Home rule - background, 1962-1980 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Home rule - background, 1962-1980 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Home rule - background, 1962-1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Walter Fauntroy, 1981-1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Mayor Barry's office, 1980-1984 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Senator Ted Kennedy, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Lobby Corps, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - D.C. voting rights testimony, 1978-1983 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - D.C. voting rights testimony, 1978-1983 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - D.C. voting rights testimony, 1978-1983 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - White House, 1978-1981 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Statehood and the Coalition, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Tax Day, April 15 1985 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Local Coalition Activities, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Project Vote Count, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - PR Group, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Series 2: Opposition Groups, 1979-1986
  Contains materials about organizations and individuals the Coalition considered opponents of self-determination for D.C. such as the Republican Party.
  - Opposition organizations, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Polls, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Ratification slates, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Pre-1983 publications, Undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Republican convention, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - D.C. Republicans for Self-Determination, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Republicans, 1975-1980 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Originals (newsletters, 1974-1983 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous documents, 1977-1983 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Mayor Barry's Breakfast for self-government, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Mayor Breakfast for voting rights, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Information packet, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Series 3: Support Groups, 1976-1985
  This series consists of reports, clippings, correspondence, pamphlets, and printed materials regarding organizations the Coalition considered supporters of its goals. A sample of groups include the American Jewish Congress, Common Cause, AFL-CIO, Democratic Party, Interfaith Conference of Metropolitan Washington, Lawyers' Committee for Civil Rights Under the Law, National Council of Churches, and the Episcopal Church.
  - D.C. Voting Rights Amendment Briefing book, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - ACLU thru Black organizations, 1977-1983 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Board of Trade thru D.C. Commission for Women, Undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Board of Trade thru D.C. Commission for Women, Undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Board of Trade thru D.C. Commission for Women, Undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Board of Trade thru D.C. Commission for Women, Undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Board of Trade thru D.C. Commission for Women, Undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Board of Trade thru D.C. Commission for Women, Undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Board of Trade thru D.C. Commission for Women, Undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Board of Trade thru D.C. Commission for Women, Undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - D.C. Congress of PTAs thru League of Women Voters-D.C., Undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - D.C. Congress of PTAs thru League of Women Voters-D.C., Undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - D.C. Congress of PTAs thru League of Women Voters-D.C., Undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - D.C. Congress of PTAs thru League of Women Voters-D.C., Undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - D.C. Congress of PTAs thru League of Women Voters-D.C., Undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - D.C. Congress of PTAs thru League of Women Voters-D.C., Undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - D.C. Congress of PTAs thru League of Women Voters-D.C., Undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - D.C. Congress of PTAs thru League of Women Voters-D.C., Undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - D.C. Congress of PTAs thru League of Women Voters-D.C., Undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - D.C. Congress of PTAs thru League of Women Voters-D.C., Undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - D.C. Congress of PTAs thru League of Women Voters-D.C., Undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - D.C. Congress of PTAs thru League of Women Voters-D.C., Undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - D.C. Congress of PTAs thru League of Women Voters-D.C., Undated (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - League of Women Voters of the U.S thru National Governor's Association, Undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - League of Women Voters of the U.S thru National Governor's Association, Undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - League of Women Voters of the U.S thru National Governor's Association, Undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - League of Women Voters of the U.S thru National Governor's Association, Undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - League of Women Voters of the U.S thru National Governor's Association, Undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - League of Women Voters of the U.S thru National Governor's Association, Undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - League of Women Voters of the U.S thru National Governor's Association, Undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - League of Women Voters of the U.S thru National Governor's Association, Undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - League of Women Voters of the U.S thru National Governor's Association, Undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - League of Women Voters of the U.S thru National Governor's Association, Undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - League of Women Voters of the U.S thru National Governor's Association, Undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - League of Women Voters of the U.S thru National Governor's Association, Undated (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - League of Women Voters of the U.S thru National Governor's Association, Undated (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - League of Women Voters of the U.S thru National Governor's Association, Undated (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - League of Women Voters of the U.S thru National Governor's Association, Undated (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - League of Women Voters of the U.S thru National Governor's Association, Undated (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - National Student Association thru United Presbyterian Church, Undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - U.S. Commission o Civil Rights thru Women's Internal League for Peace and Freedom, Undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - U.S. Commission o Civil Rights thru Women's Internal League for Peace and Freedom, Undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - U.S. Commission o Civil Rights thru Women's Internal League for Peace and Freedom, Undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - U.S. Commission o Civil Rights thru Women's Internal League for Peace and Freedom, Undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - U.S. Commission o Civil Rights thru Women's Internal League for Peace and Freedom, Undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - U.S. Commission o Civil Rights thru Women's Internal League for Peace and Freedom, Undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - U.S. Commission o Civil Rights thru Women's Internal League for Peace and Freedom, Undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - U.S. Commission o Civil Rights thru Women's Internal League for Peace and Freedom, Undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - U.S. Commission o Civil Rights thru Women's Internal League for Peace and Freedom, Undated (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - U.S. Commission o Civil Rights thru Women's Internal League for Peace and Freedom, Undated (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - U.S. Commission o Civil Rights thru Women's Internal League for Peace and Freedom, Undated (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - U.S. Commission o Civil Rights thru Women's Internal League for Peace and Freedom, Undated (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - U.S. Commission o Civil Rights thru Women's Internal League for Peace and Freedom, Undated (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - U.S. Commission o Civil Rights thru Women's Internal League for Peace and Freedom, Undated (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - U.S. Commission o Civil Rights thru Women's Internal League for Peace and Freedom, Undated (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - U.S. Commission o Civil Rights thru Women's Internal League for Peace and Freedom, Undated (Box 11, Folder 16)
- Series 4: Chronological Files, 1970-1973
  Contains internal memoranda, drafts, letters, and Coalition Comments, the Coalition's newsletter, arranged chronologically.
  - Chronological files, 1972-June 1973 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Chronological files, 1972-June 1973 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Chronological files, 1972-June 1973 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Chronological files, 1972-June 1973 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Chronological files, 1974 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Chronological files, 1974 (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Series 5: Lobbying Files, 1972-1973
  This series contains materials documenting the Coalition's lobbying efforts for home rule in 1973. Included are reports, issue papers, congressional contact lists, lobbying packets, and background materials on the House District Committee, among others.
  - Finances, 1972-1973 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Lobbying, 1973 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Strategy target lists of House members, 1973 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - National Constituency Committee, 1973 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - National Constituency Committee - sample worksheets, 1973-1974 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - National Constituency Committee - sample worksheets, 1973-1974 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - National Constituency Committee - sample worksheets, 1973-1974 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Lobby packets, August-September 1973 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - House District Committee - background materials, 1973 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Lobby efforts - National Member Organization, 1972-1973 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - League of Women Voters, Undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Local Organizations, Undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Field reports (restricted access), Undated (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Field reports (restricted access), Undated (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Field reports (restricted access), Undated (Box 15, Folder 5)
- Series 6: Media Coverage, 1972-1973
  Contains media lists from various states.
  - Media lists in various states, 1970 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Media coverage, 1972-1973 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Media coverage, 1972-1973 (Box 16, Folder 3)
- Series 7: Legislation, 1965-1973
  This series contains briefing papers, legislative analyses, congressional legislation, letters, Congressional Record excerpts, congressional voting records, and other legislative materials related to home rule.
  - Home rule, 1965 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Preparation for Coalition testimony before House Committee on the District of Columbia - Subcommittee on Government Operations, 1973 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - H.R. 9682 briefing papers used by lobbyist, 1973 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - H.R. 9682 -issues concerning the judiciary, 1973 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - H.R. 9682 -issues concerning planning, 1973 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - H.R. 9682 -letters of support, 1973 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Explanation of final action on Home Rule, 1973 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Nelson-Green Substitute proposal, 1973 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - 92nd Congress - House, 1973 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - 93rd Congress - Senate, 1973 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - 93rd Congress - House, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - 93rd Congress - House, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - 93rd Congress -Excerpts from Congressional Record, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - 93rd Congress - House of Representatives member support and voting record for home rule issues, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 4)
- Series 8: Post-Home Rule Passage, 1974
  This series includes reports, clippings, and correspondence regarding such topics as 1974 campaign financing and the formation of advisory neighborhood commissions.
  - Campaign Financing, 1974 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Advisory Neighbor Commissions, 1973-1976 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Advisory Neighbor Commissions, 1973-1976 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Advisory Neighbor Commissions, 1973-1976 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Speakers Bureau, 1974 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Committee to Support the Charter, 1974 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Salute to Volunteers, 1985 (Box 20, Folder 3)
- Series 9: Related Organizations, 1960-1971
  This series contains materials regarding two related organizations, the Home Rule Committee and Ad-Hoc Committee for Home Rule, which preceded the Coalition.
  - Home Rule Committee, 1960s (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Ad-Hoc Committee for Home Rule, 1972 (Box 20, Folder 5)
- Series 10: Research, 1966-1973
  Consists of research documents prepared by the Library of Congress regarding home rule and voting rights for D.C. Also contains legislative bills, reprints, and copies of articles on the same issues.
  - Library of Congress and other material, 1970s (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Library of Congress and other material, 1970s (Box 20, Folder 7)
- Series 11: Publications, 1973
  Primarily consists of brochures, newsletters of SDDC and other related organizations.
  - Time to Act, 1973 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Questions and Answers on D.C. Home Rules, 1973 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Home Rule for Washington - D.C. Issues and Fact, 1973 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Self-Determination for the District of Columbia: A Look at Congressional Proposals in the last 25 years, 1973 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - A Look to the Past: A Short List of the Prior Types of Governments, Undated (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Nelson Commission Recommendations, Undated (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Memorabilia, 1973 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Salute to Volunteers (duplicates), Undated (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - To Complete A Revolution" (duplicates), Undated (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Congressional Records testimony for Self-Determination (duplicates), 4/3/1973 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Coalition Comments" newsletter (duplicates), March and Sept. 1973 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Common Cause" newsletter (duplicates), 1974 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - The Home Rule Bill," Committee to Support the Charter, Undated (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Home Rule Charter Yes brochure, Undated (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Advisory Councils, Undated (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Y.O.U. for Home Rule in D.C., Undated (Box 24, Folder 3)
- Series 12: Memorabilia, ca. 1970s
  Contains brochures, buttons, bumper stickers, a patriot's hat, and banner of the Coalition. Also contains the publication Salute to Volunteers prepared by the Coalition.
  - Hat, Undated (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Banner, Undated (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Campaign literature, Undated (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Bumper stickers, Undated (Box 25, Folder 4)